<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LE 🌺 Delaney</title>
    <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ledelaney.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>LE 🌺 Delaney</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 16:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>LE 🌺 Delaney</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Four Causes of Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/talk/saberwest/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/talk/saberwest/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Cancer and Natural Selection</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/cancerspecies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/cancerspecies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of theoretical models that suggest several ways in which natural selection or individual adaptations can be detrimental to a population overall. Empirical evidence from the bacterium &lt;em&gt;Myxococcus xanthus&lt;/em&gt; has demonstrated that artifically selected &amp;ldquo;cheater&amp;rdquo; strains invade wild-type strains, ultimately causing the extinction of the entire population 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1691394/pdf/12965020.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Fiegna and Velicer 2003)&lt;/a&gt;. Yet natural selection is commonly misunderstood as an optimization process that works for the overall good of the species. This misconception is tenacious, perhaps in response to the overwhelming variety of organisms that appear perfectly designed to suit their environment. But this is not the case &amp;ndash; natural selection may be non-random, but is not goal-driven or forward-thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Four Causes of Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The influence of humans on the Earth, our inherent dependence on it, our relationship to each other, and our connection to all life — no discipline meaningfully illuminates such statements as biology does. Biology unveils the substance that serves as the blueprint for our own construction, but also demonstrates how that substance is life’s very deepest homology. That is to say, biology can offer explanation at multiple levels: first by establishing patterns and investigating their creative processes, and then by providing proximate and ultimate causes for observed patterns and processes. This dual causality — the proximate functional ‘how’ and the ultimate evolutionary ‘why’ — is both particular and of particular importance to biological sciences; the ‘why’ being the stuff that gives the ‘how’ consequence. So what does this mean for the student of biology?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of studies indicate that students maintain tenacious misconceptions regarding the evolutionary principles necessary for recognizing levels of biological explanation. To dissect these misconceptions, I administered a pre-post assignment with open-ended reflective questions to explore (1) how students construct explanations about natural selection and adaptation across several levels of postsecondary study, and (2) the extent to which their explanations change as they continue formal biology instruction. My framework, adapted from Tinbergen’s Four Questions, categorizes students’ answers based on the level of explanation addressed. I also catalog common naïve intuitions in tandem (e.g., teleological, anthropocentric, or Lamarckian inheritance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dobzhansky, T. (1973). Nothing in biology makes sense except in the light of evolution. &lt;em&gt;The American Biology Teacher, 35&lt;/em&gt;(3), 125–129.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mayr, E. (1961). Cause and effect in biology. &lt;em&gt;Science, 134&lt;/em&gt;(3489), 1501–1506.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scott, E. C. (2010). Dobzhansky was right: Let’s tell the students. &lt;em&gt;Bioessays, 32&lt;/em&gt;(5), 372–374.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tinbergen, Niko. (2005) On aims and methods of ethology. &lt;em&gt;Animal Biology 55.4&lt;/em&gt;, 297-321.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding System Distribution in the Legumes</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bslegumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 13:38:01 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bslegumes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Angiosperms maintain a diverse array of strategies to ensure successful pollination. These strategies ultimately determine the distribution of genetic variation within populations and dictate the resultant patterns of evolution, as differences in breeding systems yield differing levels of outcrossing and recombination. Although nearly half of all flowering plant species are self-incompatible (SI), the mechanisms that underpin this trait differ dramatically between families. Indeed, independent gains and the persistence of many such mechanisms across vast timescales suggests a strong role of natural selection. And yet, surprisingly little is known regarding the distribution of incompatibility systems &amp;mdash; their genetic and molecular bases, and their evolutionary relationships &amp;mdash; in most angiosperm families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of data is notable in agriculturally important Fabaceae, which contains roughly seven percent of all flowering plants. A specific type of SI &amp;mdash; S-RNase-based GSI &amp;mdash; is found in many distantly-related eudicot families, including the fairly well-studied Rosaceae. Dozens of studies hypothesize that closely-related Fabaceae shares the same system, but this remains an open question. Uncovering the answer is essential for understanding factors that influence breeding system evolution and ultimately macroevolutionary patterns in angiosperms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding System Distribution in the Orchids</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bsorchids/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 13:15:35 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bsorchids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned: more to come!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding System Distribution in the Legumes</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/publication/fabaceae-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 11:53:05 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/publication/fabaceae-poster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the enormous influence of sexual systems in determining species richness and trait distribution, there remains a surprising paucity of data regarding their distribution in some of the largest angiosperm families.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary Consequences of Plant Mating Systems</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/talk/micromorphtalk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 13:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/talk/micromorphtalk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abridged Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/teaching/abridged-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/teaching/abridged-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True learning is mostly an uncomfortable experience. Which is to say, it’s &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. Yet the rewards are enormous. You gain something that no one can ever take away from you. You are empowered. You start to believe you can climb other mountains. Bigger mountains. But at the very beginning, from the mountain base, it all feels insurmountable. It’s my job as an educator to guide every student through this process so that we can together experience the view from the top of the mountain. This starts with me: I am transparent about my own failures, I talk often about the normal but emotionally painful aspects of learning, and I do my best to provide practical tools that position students for success. No one ascends the first peak alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But biology education has a problem: it’s boring. Students commonly complain that biology is “just memorization.” Why do they say that about a subject so profound, so personally relevant to all of us? For two reasons that I use to shape my classroom. The first is that biology education lacks a framework. Biology itself has a powerful framework — evolutionary theory — but we teach each course siloed as if it’s a discipline all its own, rarely mentioning evolution (or other subdisciplines!), if at all. The second is that biology education lacks a compelling narrative. Classes usually present a series of facts devoid of connection, expecting students to appropriately place these facts within a larger organized knowledge structure on their own. This puts the onus on students to build frameworks and connect dots. How can they, when they’re so busy memorizing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The (hopeful) goal of science is to discover and disseminate truths about the universe. We are fighting to climb mountains, just as our students. But science must be about both discovery and dissemination: what good are truths that do not bring value back to society? I relentlessly reinforce that biology offers tremendously profound truths. It teaches us that we are all related, to each other, and to every other living creature on the planet. It teaches us that we all are constructed of the same amino acids, coded by the same four base pairs. It teaches us where we came from, and how the Earth cradles and shapes all of us. It teaches us the kinds of things that bring real value to our society and the lives of individuals. True understanding of biological principles creates something we desperately need: empathetic and engaged citizens that care for the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Course Websites</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/teaching/course-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/teaching/course-websites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-websites--materials&#34;&gt;Course Websites &amp;amp; Materials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mendelian--molecular-genetics&#34;&gt;Mendelian &amp;amp; Molecular Genetics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ledelaney.org/summer2020.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BIOS 220: Summer 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ledelaney.org/spring2020.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BIOS 220: Spring 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ledelaney/Genetics220&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub repo with additional materials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;general-ecology-laboratory&#34;&gt;General Ecology Laboratory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ledelaney/GeneralEcologyMaterials&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BIOS 331: Modeling Assignments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
