<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | L. E. Delaney</title>
    <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ledelaney.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Cancer and Natural Selection</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/cancerspecies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/cancerspecies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of theoretical models that suggest several ways in which natural selection or individual adaptations can be detrimental to a population overall. Empirical evidence from the bacterium &lt;em&gt;Myxococcus xanthus&lt;/em&gt; has demonstrated that artifically selected &amp;ldquo;cheater&amp;rdquo; strains invade wild-type strains, ultimately causing the extinction of the entire population 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1691394/pdf/12965020.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Fiegna and Velicer 2003)&lt;/a&gt;. Yet natural selection is commonly misunderstood as an optimization process that works for the overall good of the species. This misconception is tenacious, perhaps in response to the overwhelming variety of organisms that appear perfectly designed to suit their environment. But this is not the case &amp;ndash; natural selection may be non-random, but is not goal-driven or forward-thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Logic of Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of studies illustrate that students maintain tenacious misconceptions regarding the evolutionary principles necessary for recognizing levels of biological explanation. To dissect these misconceptions, we administered a pre-post assignment with open-ended reflective questions to explore (1) how students construct explanations about natural selection and adaptation across several levels of postsecondary study, and (2) the extent to which their explanations change as they continue formal biology instruction. Our framework, adapted from Tinbergen&amp;rsquo;s Four Questions, categorized students&amp;rsquo; answers based on the level of explanation addressed. In addition, we cataloged common naïve intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dobzhansky, T. (1973). Nothing in biology makes sense except in the light of evolution. &lt;em&gt;The American Biology Teacher, 35&lt;/em&gt;(3), 125–129.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayr, E. (1961). Cause and effect in biology. &lt;em&gt;Science, 134&lt;/em&gt;(3489), 1501–1506.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott, E. C. (2010). Dobzhansky was right: Let’s tell the students. &lt;em&gt;Bioessays, 32&lt;/em&gt;(5), 372–374.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding Systems in the Legumes</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bslegumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 13:38:01 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bslegumes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Angiosperms maintain a diverse array of strategies to ensure successful pollination. These strategies ultimately determine the distribution of genetic variation within populations and dictate the resultant patterns of evolution, as differences in breeding systems yield differing levels of outcrossing and recombination. Although nearly half of all flowering plant species are self-incompatible (SI), the mechanisms that underpin this trait differ dramatically between families. Indeed, independent gains and the persistence of many such mechanisms across vast timescales suggests a strong role of natural selection. And yet, surprisingly little is known regarding the distribution of incompatibility systems &amp;mdash; their genetic and molecular bases, and their evolutionary relationships &amp;mdash; in most angiosperm families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of data is notable in agriculturally important Fabaceae, which contains roughly seven percent of all flowering plants. A specific type of SI &amp;mdash; S-RNase-based GSI &amp;mdash; is found in many distantly-related eudicot families, including the fairly well-studied Rosaceae. Dozens of studies hypothesize that closely-related Fabaceae shares the same system, but this remains an open question. Uncovering the answer is essential for understanding factors that influence breeding system evolution and ultimately macroevolutionary patterns in angiosperms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding Systems in the Orchids</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bsorchids/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 13:15:35 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bsorchids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned: more to come!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
