<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | L. E. Delaney</title>
    <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ledelaney.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Logic of Adaptation: How Do Students Reason about Natural Selection?</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding Systems in the Orchids</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bsorchids/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 13:38:35 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bsorchids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned: more to come!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding Systems in the Legumes</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bslegumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 13:15:01 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/bslegumes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Angiosperms maintain a diverse array of strategies to ensure successful pollination. These strategies ultimately determine the distribution of genetic variation within populations and dictate the resultant patterns of evolution, as differences in breeding systems yield differing levels of outcrossing and recombination. Although nearly half of all flowering plant species are self-incompatible (SI), the mechanisms that underpin this trait differ dramatically between families. Indeed, independent gains and the persistence of many such mechanisms across vast timescales suggests a strong role of natural selection. And yet, surprisingly little is known regarding the distribution of incompatibility systems &amp;mdash; their genetic and molecular bases, and their evolutionary relationships &amp;mdash; in most angiosperm families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of data is notable in agriculturally important Fabaceae, which contains roughly seven percent of all flowering plants. A specific type of SI &amp;ndash; S-RNase-based GSI &amp;ndash; is found in many distantly-related eudicot families, including the fairly well-studied Rosaceae. Dozens of studies hypothesize that closely-related Fabaceae shares the same system, but this remains an open question. Uncovering the answer is essential for understanding factors that influence breeding system evolution and ultimately macroevolutionary patterns in angiosperms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
