<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Evolution Outreach | LE 🌺Delaney</title>
    <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/tags/evolution-outreach/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ledelaney.github.io/tags/evolution-outreach/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Evolution Outreach</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Evolution Outreach</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/tags/evolution-outreach/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Four Causes of Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 14:00:42 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ledelaney.github.io/project/logicadaptation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The influence of humans on the Earth, our inherent dependence on it, our relationship to each other, and our connection to all life — no discipline meaningfully illuminates such statements as biology does. Biology unveils the substance that serves as the blueprint for our own construction, but also demonstrates how that substance is life’s very deepest homology. That is to say, biology can offer explanation at multiple levels: first by establishing patterns and investigating their creative processes, and then by providing proximate and ultimate causes for observed patterns and processes. This dual causality — the proximate functional ‘how’ and the ultimate evolutionary ‘why’ — is both particular and of particular importance to biological sciences; the ‘why’ being the stuff that gives the ‘how’ consequence. So what does this mean for the student of biology?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of studies indicate that students maintain tenacious misconceptions regarding the evolutionary principles necessary for recognizing levels of biological explanation. To dissect these misconceptions, I administered a pre-post assignment with open-ended reflective questions to explore (1) how students construct explanations about natural selection and adaptation across several levels of postsecondary study, and (2) the extent to which their explanations change as they continue formal biology instruction. My framework, adapted from Tinbergen’s Four Questions, categorizes students’ answers based on the level of explanation addressed. I also catalog common naïve intuitions in tandem (e.g., teleological, anthropocentric, or Lamarckian inheritance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dobzhansky, T. (1973). Nothing in biology makes sense except in the light of evolution. &lt;em&gt;The American Biology Teacher, 35&lt;/em&gt;(3), 125–129.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mayr, E. (1961). Cause and effect in biology. &lt;em&gt;Science, 134&lt;/em&gt;(3489), 1501–1506.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scott, E. C. (2010). Dobzhansky was right: Let’s tell the students. &lt;em&gt;Bioessays, 32&lt;/em&gt;(5), 372–374.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tinbergen, Niko. (2005) On aims and methods of ethology. &lt;em&gt;Animal Biology 55.4&lt;/em&gt;, 297-321.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
